<?xml version="1.0"?>
<site xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="tree.xsd">
        <nodes>
                <node id="home">
                        <title>I am</title>
                        <body>
                                <p><b>Endre Borza</b>, and I made this to compile and present
                                information about myself. </p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="i-made" />
                                <child ref="i-like" />
                                <child ref="i-use" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="i-made">
                        <title>I made</title>
                        <body>
                                <ul>
                                        <li><a href="https://www.rankless.org/">Rankless</a>, an
                                interactive visualization platform built on massive scholarly
                                datasets </li>
                                        <li> Contributions to academic papers where the data was too
                                large or complex to handle conventionally </li>
                                        <li> Machine learning and optimization software for
                                logistics and football analytics </li>
                                        <li> Curricula for courses on programming, data engineering,
                                and applied ML </li>
                                        <li> A collection of small, open-source tools that make my
                                work easier </li>
                                </ul>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="rankless" />
                                <child ref="academia" />
                                <child ref="profession" />
                                <child ref="applets" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="i-like">
                        <title>I like</title>
                        <body>
                                <ul>
                                        <li> Knowledge management </li>
                                        <li> Health and longevity </li>
                                        <li> Football, D&amp;D, StarCraft, chess </li>
                                        <li> Film and popular culture </li>
                                </ul>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="football" />
                                <child ref="dnd" />
                                <child ref="culture" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="i-use">
                        <title>I use</title>
                        <body>
                                <ul>
                                        <li> Python, Rust, Svelte to build </li>
                                        <li> Neovim, Linux, LeftWM, split keyboards </li>
                                        <li> AI mostly from the command line, selectively but
                                appreciatively </li>
                                </ul>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="config" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="academia">
                        <title>Research &amp; Teaching</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Since around 2014 I have been working on the data side of a bunch
                                of <b>papers</b> and one <a href="https://gabors-data-analysis.com/">
                                book</a>, first I got some "thanks" in the acknowledgments, then I
                                started to get <a
                                                href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=FzM5hAUAAAAJ&amp;hl=en&amp;oi=ao">credit
                                as an author</a>. There is a wide scope of topics here, from
                                experimental economics, to park visitation patterns. The common
                                thread is large, complex datasets that needed efficient processing,
                                or creative analysis.</p>
        <p>In 2015 I started <b>teaching</b> @ <a
                                                href="http://rajk.eu/home/">Rajk</a>, and since then
                                have taught courses in Programming and Algorithm Design, Applied
                                Algorithm Design for Data Processing, and Statistical Methods for
                                Causal Inference. I am also sometimes a guest instructor in machine
                                learning and network science courses, both at rajk and at Corvinus
                                University.</p>
        <p>Turns out, I quite like teaching, and Rajk, with
                                small classes and generally motivated students, was a great fit. I
                                even got awarded the Permanent Professors of Rajk College title,
                                which might be my favorite thing I've got as an accolade and the one
                                thing I will brag about without anyone asking.</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="profession">
                        <title>Private Sector Work</title>
                        <body>
                                <h2>Data Science @ Lidl</h2>
        <p>2018-2021 I worked at Lidl as a data
                                scientist. It was interesting, challenging, paid well, I learned a
                                lot. It was a demanding environment with high employee turnover but
                                still high productivity. After a few years, I got tired of not being
                                able to show anything I've done to anybody, and not owning any of
                                the fruits of my labor, so I took a massive pay cut and moved to
                                academia.</p>
        <h2>Freelance</h2>
        <p>Since I primarily work in academia
                                since 2021, I did set up a gig where I can do consulting and
                                development contract work still in the private sector. I find that
                                it is nice to meet challenges that have market value and it's nice
                                to get paid well. I had so far done some machine learning modeling
                                and some highly convoluted data-collection. One of the drawbacks
                                next to these great private sector benefits is that one can't really
                                go into much detail.</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="lidl" />
                                <child ref="football" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="rankless">
                        <title>Rankless</title>
                        <body>
                                <a href="https://www.rankless.org/">Rankless</a>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="ccl" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="applets">
                        <title>Lots of Building</title>
                        <zoomedBody>
                                <p>Small projects and contributions</p>
                        </zoomedBody>
                        <body>
                                <p><strong>Libraries</strong> to read/write <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/shackleton">
                                parquet</a> and <a href="https://github.com/endremborza/partcsv">csv</a>
                                in a parallel and efficient way in python. Entity coreference in
                                both <a href="https://github.com/endremborza/encoref">python</a> and <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/Encoref.jl">
                                Julia</a>, a <a href="https://github.com/endremborza/BigO.jl">Julia
                                library</a> for complexity plotting and estimation.</p>
        <p><strong>
                                Apps</strong> like <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/scimagojr-search-engine">a
                                browser extension</a> to search for a scientific journal with one
                                right-click (and then a left-click), a small <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/typegame">dash
                                app</a> for creating quizzes for programming education, docker-based <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/fibonacci_language_comparison">comparison
                                tool</a> of programming languages, running the same algorithm, with
                                an interface for guessing results. Also a bunch of apps for <a
                                                href="http://rajk.eu/home/">rajk</a> college, where
                                I spent a wonderful 7 years and got to make tools for resolving
                                preference-based <a href="https://github.com/rajk-apps/riki">course
                                applications</a>, uploading coursework, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/rajk-apps/rajksimple">credit-card
                                processing</a>, teaching aids for <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/teach">
                                presenting</a> or <a
                                                href="https://jkg-evaluators.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html">
                                evaluation</a>, tinder-like quick evaluation tools for collective
                                decision making and many failed others. I tried vanilla javascript
                                with google sheets backends, raw PHP 5, and eventually Django. Most
                                of them got the job done at the time, but for me the biggest benefit
                                was getting my hands dirty, even before working together with a
                                group of senior, experienced developers later.</p>
        <p>These are
                                mostly some sort of software that all become stale as versions move
                                on. <strong>Simple tools</strong>, are fun because they can just be <em>
                                done</em>, like an interactive <a
                                                href="https://endremborza.github.io/funtum-computing/">
                                article</a> explaining quantum states and gates with hand-rolled 3d
                                SVGs of Bloch-spheres, or a <a
                                                href="https://endremborza.github.io/static-snippets/box">
                                tool</a> that helps my friend figure out how to cut a few pieces of
                                wood to make a house-like bed for my godson.</p>
        <h4>Other Repos</h4>
        <ul>
                                        <li>aswan</li>
                                        <li>sqlmermaid</li>
                                        <li>atqo</li>
                                        <li>datazimmer</li>
                                        <li>parquetranger</li>
                                        <li>partcsv</li>
                                        <li>shackleton</li>
                                        <li>branthebuilder</li>
                                </ul>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="ccl">
                        <title>CCL @ Corvinus</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Started working in 2023 as a Research Data Engineer at <a
                                                href="https://centerforcollectivelearning.org/">ccl</a>,
                                a multidisciplinary lab started in Budapest by an EU grant. I help
                                others publish papers involving complex data pipelines, but mostly I
                                worked on <a href="https://www.rankless.org/">rankless.org</a> - a
                                platform for the exploration of scholarly data. I managed to
                                convince our director C&#xE9;sar - whose idea the site itself
                                actually was - that I'd do the whole thing in Rust and Svelte
                                without any large framework or ready-made tech like react, neo4j, or
                                even anything SQL.</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="rankless" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="krtk">
                        <title>Research Big Data Team @ KRTK</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>In 2021 I set up a small team called <a
                                                href="https://sscu-budapest.github.io/">Social
                                Science Computing Unit Budapest</a> and we started to build a
                                comprehensive data science toolset for scientific research. It
                                slowed down a lot due to a range of issues, mostly around demand,
                                but we did build a central dataset and data-project
                                standard/framework named <a
                                                href="https://github.com/sscu-budapest/datazimmer">
                                datazimmer</a>.</p>
        <p>We also built tools around it like <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/colassigner">
                                colassigner</a> so that we don't use string literals with pandas so
                                much, <a href="https://github.com/endremborza/parquetranger">
                                parquetranger</a> to manage - save, load, extend - large datasets in
                                partitioned parquet files, a task queue orchestrator <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/atqo">atqo</a>,
                                raw data collection manager <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/aswan">aswan</a>
                                - named after a dam, and some python package boilerplate <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/branthebuilder">
                                branthebuilder</a> so that we can start many others.</p>
        <p>We also
                                set up a <em>lot</em> of datasets for research around retail,
                                weather, job-listings, chess, real-estate, football, news articles,
                                interconnected wiki-pages, movies, etc. many of them periodically,
                                automatically updating. I'm still working on it as of 2025.</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="lidl">
                        <title>Data Science @ Lidl</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>We developed machine learning for demand prediction and
                                algorithms to optimize delivery and distribution. We were quite
                                successful, a lot of what we did got scaled up and is being used by
                                Lidl widely. I also got to work with professional developers and
                                infra people and gain experience with technologies less frequently
                                used in data science jobs like Kubernetes, Kafka, Elasticsearch, a <em>
                                lot</em> of CI/CD and so on. I hope they don't sue me for exposing a
                                few things they use. Lidl is very protective and litigious</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="teaching">
                        <title>Teaching</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>In 2015 I started teaching @ <a href="http://rajk.eu/home/">Rajk</a>,
                                and since then have taught courses in Programming and Algorithm
                                Design, Applied Algorithm Design for Data Processing, Statistical
                                Methods for Causal Inference. I am also sometimes a guest instructor
                                in machine learning and network science courses, both at rajk and at
                                Corvinus.</p>
        <p>Turns out, I quite like teaching, and Rajk, with
                                small classes and generally motivated students, was a great fit. I
                                even got awarded the Permanent Professors of Rajk College title,
                                which might be my favorite thing I've got as an accolade and the one
                                thing I will brag about without anyone asking.</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="contributions">
                        <title>Contributions</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>I think open-source contributions are a great way to learn, and
                                so a while I did a bit of that but lost a bit of interest recently.
                                However, I managed to contribute to <a
                                                href="https://github.com/pandas-dev/pandas/commits?author=endremborza">
                                pandas</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/dask/dask/commits?author=endremborza">
                                dask</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/pandas-profiling/pandas-profiling/commits?author=endremborza">
                                pandas-profiling</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/JuliaLang/julia/commits?author=endremborza">
                                julia</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/fsspec/filesystem_spec/commits?author=endremborza">
                                fsspec</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/iterative/dvc/commits?author=endremborza">
                                dvc</a>.</p>
        <p>What was really nice however, is <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/sqlmermaid">a
                                project of mine</a> that visualizes sql schemas with python even got
                                a PR from a random person. I merged it, it was lovely, since I never
                                really promote any of this.</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
        </nodes>
</site>

