<?xml version="1.0"?>
<site xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="tree.xsd">
        <nodes>
                <node id="home">
                        <title>I am</title>
                        <body>
                                <p><b>Endre Borza</b>. I made this page to compile and present
                                information about myself. </p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="artifacts" />
                                <child ref="academia" />
                                <child ref="tools-tastes" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="artifacts">
                        <title>Artifacts</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>I built</p>
                                <ul>
                                        <li><a href="https://www.rankless.org/">Rankless</a>, an
                                interactive visualization platform built on massive scholarly
                                datasets </li>
                                        <li> Machine learning and optimization software for
                                logistics and football analytics </li>
                                        <li> A collection of small, open-source tools that make my
                                work easier </li>
                                </ul>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="rankless" />
                                <child ref="data-at-scale" />
                                <child ref="applets" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="academia">
                        <title>Research &amp; Teaching</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Since <b>2014</b> I have been working on the data side of a bunch
                                of <b>papers</b> and one <a href="https://gabors-data-analysis.com/">
                                book</a>, first I got some "thanks" in the acknowledgments, then I
                                started to get <a
                                                href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=FzM5hAUAAAAJ&amp;hl=en&amp;oi=ao">credit
                                as an author</a>. There is a wide scope of topics here, from
                                experimental economics, to park visitation patterns. The common
                                thread is large, complex datasets that needed efficient processing,
                                or creative analysis.</p>
                                <p>In 2015 I started <b>teaching</b> @ <a
                                                href="http://rajk.eu/home/">Rajk</a>, and since then
                                have taught courses in Programming and Algorithm Design, Applied
                                Algorithm Design for Data Processing, and Statistical Methods for
                                Causal Inference. I am also sometimes a guest instructor in machine
                                learning and network science courses, both at rajk and at Corvinus
                                University.</p>
                                <p>Turns out, I quite like teaching, and Rajk, with
                                small classes and generally motivated students, was a great fit. I
                                even got awarded the Permanent Professors of Rajk College title,
                                which might be my favorite thing I've got as an accolade and the one
                                thing I will brag about without anyone asking.</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="papers" />
                                <child ref="teaching" />
                                <child ref="research-infra" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="tools-tastes">
                        <title>Tools &amp; Tastes</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>I use</p>
                                <ul>
                                        <li> Python, Rust, Svelte to build </li>
                                        <li> Neovim, Linux, LeftWM, split keyboards </li>
                                        <li> AI mostly from the command line, selectively but
                                appreciatively </li>
                                </ul>
                                <p>I like</p>
                                <ul>
                                        <li> Knowledge management </li>
                                        <li> Health and longevity </li>
                                        <li> Football, D&amp;D, StarCraft, chess </li>
                                        <li> Film and popular culture </li>
                                </ul>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="work-environment" />
                                <child ref="play" />
                                <child ref="culture" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="rankless">
                        <title>Rankless</title>
                        <body>
                                <p><a href="https://www.rankless.org/">Rankless</a> was a great
                                engineering challenge. I got to make a pipeline that processes over
                                3 billion citations among 300 million papers, and ends up with an
                                app that responds to the most intricate breakdown requests
                                practically instantly. To do this you really need to heavily
                                optimize everything. A specialized Rust backend that has multi stage
                                compilation that aligns to the shape and size of the data, plus a
                                Svelte front-end with hand-rolled SVGs, no dependencies, as
                                performant as it comes</p>
                                <p> It was Cesar's idea at <a
                                                href="https://centerforcollectivelearning.org/">ccl</a>
                                </p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="ccl" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="data-at-scale">
                        <title>Data at Scale</title>
                        <body>
                                <h4>Retail Data Science</h4>
                                <p><b>2018</b>-<b>2021</b> I worked at
                                Lidl as a data scientist. It was interesting, challenging, paid
                                well, I learned a lot. It was a demanding environment with high
                                employee turnover but still high productivity. After a few years, I
                                got tired of not being able to show anything I've done to anybody,
                                and not owning any of the fruits of my labor, so I took a massive
                                pay cut and moved to academia.</p>
                                <h4>Freelance</h4>
                                <p>Since I
                                primarily work in academia since <b>2021</b>, I did set up a gig
                                where I can do consulting and development contract work still in the
                                private sector. I find that it is nice to meet challenges that have
                                market value and it's nice to get paid well. I had so far done some
                                machine learning modeling and some highly convoluted
                                data-collection. One of the drawbacks next to these great private
                                sector benefits is that one can't really go into much detail.</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="retail-ml" />
                                <child ref="football-ml" />
                                <child ref="research-infra" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="applets">
                        <title>Applets</title>
                        <body>
                                <p><strong>Libraries</strong> to read/write <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/shackleton">
                                parquet</a> and <a href="https://github.com/endremborza/partcsv">csv</a>
                                in a parallel and efficient way in python. Entity coreference in
                                both <a href="https://github.com/endremborza/encoref">python</a> and <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/Encoref.jl">
                                Julia</a>, a <a href="https://github.com/endremborza/BigO.jl">Julia
                                library</a> for complexity plotting and estimation.</p>
                                <p><strong>
                                Apps</strong> like <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/scimagojr-search-engine">a
                                browser extension</a> to search for a scientific journal with one
                                right-click (and then a left-click), a small <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/typegame">dash
                                app</a> for creating quizzes for programming education, docker-based <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/fibonacci_language_comparison">comparison
                                tool</a> of programming languages, running the same algorithm, with
                                an interface for guessing results. Also a bunch of apps for <a
                                                href="http://rajk.eu/home/">rajk</a> college, where
                                I spent a wonderful 7 years and got to make tools for resolving
                                preference-based <a href="https://github.com/rajk-apps/riki">course
                                applications</a>, uploading coursework, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/rajk-apps/rajksimple">credit-card
                                processing</a>, teaching aids for <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/teach">
                                presenting</a> or <a
                                                href="https://jkg-evaluators.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html">
                                evaluation</a>, tinder-like quick evaluation tools for collective
                                decision making and many failed others. I tried vanilla javascript
                                with google sheets backends, raw PHP 5, and eventually Django. Most
                                of them got the job done at the time, but the biggest benefit was
                                getting my hands dirty, even before working together with a group of
                                senior developers later.</p>
                                <p>These are mostly some sort of
                                software that all become stale as versions move on. <strong>Simple
                                tools</strong>, are fun because they can just be <em> done</em>,
                                like an interactive <a
                                                href="https://endremborza.github.io/funtum-computing/">
                                article</a> explaining quantum states and gates with hand-rolled 3d
                                SVGs of Bloch-spheres, or a <a
                                                href="https://endremborza.github.io/static-snippets/box">
                                tool</a> that helps my friend figure out how to cut a few pieces of
                                wood to make a house-like bed for my godson.</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="open-source" />
                                <child ref="my-tools" />
                                <child ref="sscub-tools" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="retail-ml">
                        <title>Retail at Industrial Scale</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Starting in <b>2018</b> at Lidl, we developed machine learning
                                for demand prediction and algorithms to optimize delivery and
                                distribution. We were quite successful, a lot of what we did got
                                scaled up and is being used by Lidl widely. I also got to work with
                                experienced developers and infra people plus technologies less
                                frequently used in data science jobs like Kubernetes, Kafka,
                                Elasticsearch, a <em>lot</em> of CI/CD and so on. </p>
                                <p>I quit
                                mostly because I wanted more ownership of my work. It was ruthless,
                                difficult and great</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="football-ml">
                        <title>Football Analytics</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Worked on ML models and iterative algorithm design for evaluating
                                team performance, player value and contract terms</p>
                                <p>Worked on a
                                few papers, where in some cases complex football was used to draw
                                parallels with other fields, or just analyzed the behaviour of
                                referees</p>
                                <p>I sometimes create small pieces of analysis about
                                football for myself, I rarely share it but <a
                                                href="https://bits.borza.cc/pl-fixtures">here</a> is
                                one about the difficulty of partitions of Premier League fixtures.</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="football-fun" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="research-infra">
                        <title>Research Infrastructure</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>FILL</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="ccl" />
                                <child ref="sscub-tools" />
                                <child ref="sscub" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="my-tools">
                        <title>My Applets</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Small libraries for parallel IO, data handling, and analysis
                                support. - FILL</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="work-environment" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="open-source">
                        <title>Open Source</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Open-source contributions are a great way to learn, and in many
                                cases the best way to truly understand a tool is to make yourself be
                                able to improve it. So for a while I did a bit of that but lost
                                interest recently. I contributed to <a
                                                href="https://github.com/pandas-dev/pandas/commits?author=endremborza">
                                pandas</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/dask/dask/commits?author=endremborza">
                                dask</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/pandas-profiling/pandas-profiling/commits?author=endremborza">
                                pandas-profiling</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/JuliaLang/julia/commits?author=endremborza">
                                the Julia language</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/fsspec/filesystem_spec/commits?author=endremborza">
                                fsspec</a>, <a
                                                href="https://github.com/iterative/dvc/commits?author=endremborza">
                                and dvc</a>.</p>

                                <p><a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/sqlmermaid">A
                                project of mine</a> that visualizes sql schemas with python even got
                                a PR from a random person. I merged it, it was lovely, since I never
                                really promote any of this.</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="sscub-tools">
                        <title>Research Tooling</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>In a team I built a central dataset and data-project
                                standard/framework named <a
                                                href="https://github.com/sscu-budapest/datazimmer">
                                datazimmer</a>.</p>
                                <p>We also built tools around it like <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/colassigner">
                                colassigner</a> so that we don't use string literals with pandas so
                                much, <a href="https://github.com/endremborza/parquetranger">
                                parquetranger</a> to manage - save, load, extend - large datasets in
                                partitioned parquet files, a task queue orchestrator <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/atqo">atqo</a>,
                                raw data collection manager <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/aswan">aswan</a>
                                - named after a dam, and some python package boilerplate <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/branthebuilder">
                                branthebuilder</a> so that we can start many others.</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="sscub" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="papers">
                        <title>Papers</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Contributions to academic research through data engineering and
                                scalable analysis. - FILL</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="teaching">
                        <title>Teaching</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Teaching programming and data-heavy methods in small, motivated
                                settings. - FILL</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="ccl">
                        <title>Center for Collective Learning</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Started working in 2023 as a Research Data Engineer at <a
                                                href="https://centerforcollectivelearning.org/">ccl</a>,
                                a multidisciplinary lab started in Budapest by an EU grant. I help
                                others publish papers involving complex data pipelines, but mostly I
                                worked on <a href="https://www.rankless.org/">rankless.org</a> - a
                                platform for the exploration of scholarly data. I managed to
                                convince our director that I'd do the whole thing in Rust and Svelte
                                without any large framework or ready-made tech like react, neo4j, or
                                even anything SQL.</p>
                                <p>I also was responsible for setting up
                                working environments for data heavy computations in research.</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="sscub">
                        <title>Social Science Computing</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>In 2021 I set up a small team called <a
                                                href="https://sscu-budapest.github.io/">Social
                                Science Computing Unit Budapest</a> at the Centre for Economic and
                                Regional Studies. We started to build a comprehensive data science
                                toolset for scientific research. It slowed down a lot due to a range
                                of issues, mostly around demand, but we did build a central dataset
                                and data-project standard/framework and set up a <em>lot</em> of
                                datasets for research around retail, weather, job-listings, chess,
                                real-estate, football, news articles, interconnected wiki-pages,
                                movies, etc. many of them periodically, automatically updating.</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="work-environment">
                        <title>Work Environment</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>I like having everything being derived from code, easily
                                reproducible. I try keeping everything I need that is necessary to
                                setup a working environment for myself in one place <a
                                                href="https://github.com/endremborza/setup">here</a>.
                                It's not always perfectly up to date and comprehensive, but it
                                reflects how I work.</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="play">
                        <title>Games &amp; Play</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>Structured play that rewards systems thinking. - FILL</p>
                        </body>
                        <children>
                                <child ref="dnd" />
                                <child ref="football-fun" />
                        </children>
                </node>
                <node id="dnd">
                        <title>D&amp;D</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>I started playing in 2020, and it turned out to be one of my
                                primary recreational activities.</p>
                                <p>I find that running a D &amp;
                                D campaign is the ultimate test of any incorporeal inventory and
                                note-taking system. You need to build a world, quickly retrieve
                                information, very quickly input new information, and keep track of
                                the knowledge of the world from the point of view of several PCs and
                                NPCs. After trying a great number of options from the PKM and
                                note-taking space, I settled for the time on <a
                                                href="https://github.com/logseq/logseq">Logseq</a>,
                                but am constantly building and improving my setup. </p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="football-fun">
                        <title>Football for Fun</title>
                        <body><p>Play, like - FILL</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
                <node id="culture">
                        <title>Culture - RENAME</title>
                        <body>
                                <p>I like writing short reviews from time to time about films,
                                games, albums as it is great practice in expression. <a
                                                href="https://www.imdb.com/user/ur23979373/reviews">Film
                                reviews</a> are public on imdb, <a
                                                href="https://rateyourmusic.com/~endremborza">music</a>is
                                going a lot slower</p>
                        </body>
                </node>
        </nodes>
</site>
